<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>moorepants - advocacy</title><link href="https://moorepants.github.io/moorepants.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://moorepants.github.io/moorepants.info/feeds/advocacy.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://moorepants.github.io/moorepants.info/</id><updated>2019-11-15T06:50:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>a websitee</subtitle><entry><title>Comments from a concerned Sacramento citizen and Intercampus Shuttle rider regarding the proposed SacRT/YCTD/UCD public transit route</title><link href="https://moorepants.github.io/moorepants.info/blog/sacrt-yctd-letter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-15T06:50:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T06:50:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:moorepants.github.io,2019-11-15:/moorepants.info/blog/sacrt-yctd-letter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://objects-us-east-1.dream.io/moorepants/shuttle-cartoon.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sent to the board members on November 10th, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SacRT and YCTD Board Members,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have ridden the UCD Intercampus Shuttle daily for the last 4.5 years. Neither
my wife nor I own a car and I either walk, bicycle, or use mass transit to get
everywhere I need …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://objects-us-east-1.dream.io/moorepants/shuttle-cartoon.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sent to the board members on November 10th, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SacRT and YCTD Board Members,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have ridden the UCD Intercampus Shuttle daily for the last 4.5 years. Neither
my wife nor I own a car and I either walk, bicycle, or use mass transit to get
everywhere I need to go in life and have done so for 18 years. I accepted my
job at UC Davis and chose my home location in Sacramento based on the fact that
there is a flexible hourly direct transit option from the UCD Med Center to the
UCD campus. This is a service UCD has offered to their employees consistently
for over 30 years, which is by now inherently an employee benefit. This allows
my wife and I to have good jobs in the two cities, although the commute for me
is still just tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, UC Davis is abandoning me and upwards of 500 other students,
staff, faculty, and patients by eliminating this shuttle as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an ardent supporter of public and private efforts to reduce the number of
cars in our transportation system by introducing options that are better, more
convenient, and more affordable than driving an automobile. The most obvious
and maximally impactful solution for lowering emissions, reducing traffic
congestion, reducing traffic fatalities, and increasing people's travel
happiness is removing single occupancy vehicles from the road in favor of mass
transit. For example, moving a passenger from a single occupancy vehicle to a
diesel bus reduces per person total emissions 9 times more than switching a
passenger from a diesel bus to an electric bus &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id6" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is no evidence that the proposed elimination of UCD's
Intercampus Shuttle will reduce the number of cars. In fact, the riders'
anecdotal and emerging objective evidence points to many of the 500 shuttle
riders finding other ways to get across the causeway, most likely in single
occupancy vehicles. SacRT and YCTD are banking almost completely on UCD
providing 500 weekly riders and more than $600,000 per year to subsidize this
public route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People chose among commute options based on a large set of factors, some of
which are transit frequency and transit power energy source. But research shows
that commute duration is a vastly larger concern than frequency, especially for
travel between cities &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id7" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Research also shows that happiness in one's commute
is a large factor in choosing the commute option &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id8" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id9" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. For better or worse,
private shuttles for workers are consistently rated better than public options
for happiness and preference &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id7" id="id5"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The good thing is that any well occupied bus,
public or private, is removing cars from the roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this research in mind, UC Davis did zero investigation of the 500+ current
shuttle riders to determine whether they would prefer the proposed new transit
route before they made seemingly immovable decisions that drastically affect
mine and the other riders' lives. SacRT, YCTD, the City of Sacramento, and the
City of Davis followed suit and collected little to no hard evidence to support
their claims that making the change as proposed will decrease vehicles on the
causeway or make for a better commute for the likely riders. The parties
involved have now been awarded millions of public dollars with virtually no
evidence to back their inflated claims in the associated grant proposals. This
is not how public agencies and research universities should be making
decisions. As a professor that explicitly trains engineers to stick to evidence
informed decision making, it is shameful that the agencies involved would
violate this social contract with the public, their students, and their
employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not yet understand why UC Davis, SacRT, YCTD, and the cities' leadership
are so fixated on this exact proposed plan when hundreds of current shuttle
riders have repeatedly and clearly expressed how this plan will negatively
affect them. Two hundred of the ~500 current riders concerns are expressed in
detail at our website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.acrossthecauseway.com"&gt;www.acrossthecauseway.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 600 individuals have signed their names to the letter to express their
support for the terms outlined there. Chancellor May and Vice Chancellor
Lubarsky, Health Campus CEO, did not respond directly to our letter and have
seemingly dismissed our requests of retaining the shuttle and having seats at
the decision making table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they and you gave us a seat at that table, we could discuss the many
alternatives that are both better for the public and for the current shuttle
riders. Why the involved agencies are not considering these is unbeknownst to
me and the other riders. For example, here are some alternatives that should
satisfy all concerned parties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retain the UCD shuttle exactly as it is, except allow the public to buy
tickets. The fares from the public ticket sales can be used to increase
capacity if there is demand. The buses awarded to the regional transit
agencies can then be used to improve other routes. There is a SacRT/YCTD
2036 goal to ultimately convert all buses to electric, so why can't it be
started on other existing public routes where there would be no turmoil?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retain the UCD shuttle exactly as it is. Add the planned public bus route
adjacent as proposed with the electric buses. Do both. This increases
capacity, frequency, and transit options for the public and does not degrade
the current service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retain the UCD shuttle exactly as it is. Use the electric buses to make the
42A/B have higher frequency and express options AND/OR to make the 43/43R/44
more frequent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement the proposed line and eliminate the existing shuttle but retain
all of the most important features that the current shuttle riders want:
hourly direct service med center&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;mondavi center, no increase in direct
service commute duration, seat belts on all seats, $1.50/ride cost,
$45/month cost, seats for all people at peak times, 5:30AM-9:00PM operating
time, extra stops on campus for those that don't/can't walk as far (genome
center/silo), 10+ bicycles carried per bus, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these options and more are possible. The leaders can make changes
without enraging the current riders and causing them to find other
transportation across the causeway or, even worse, quitting their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concerned 200+ riders have reached out directly to Chancellor May and Vice
Chancellor Lubarsky over a week ago. Both have dismissed our letter and
concerns for all intents and purposes. We do not understand why the Chancellors
have so little regard for their staff's, students', faculty's, and patients'
opinions. Chancellor May, just last week, addressed 500 other employee's
concern about lack of pay almost instantly yet we only get to talk to the
Chancellor's stonewalling government relations officer. We are not government!
We are UCD's employees and students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SacRT and YCTD still have a chance to be outstanding public agencies by
postponing the decisions that will result in the elimination of the UCD
Intercampus Shuttle and telling UC Davis that they must address the riders'
concerns. With this extended time and a requirement to include the riders in
decision making, surely an alternative solution that suits all parties involved
(including the actual riders) can be reached, likely with a design that makes
transit better for everyone across the causeway. I plead with the transit
agencies to do this for me, the existing 500+ riders, and potential future
riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Jason K. Moore, PhD&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty, Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering Department&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Member, Institute of Transportation Studies&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;University of California, Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;8.9 = (410 gCO2/passenger/mile [SOV] - 11 gCO2/passenger/mile [EV Bus
Freeway])/(56 gCO2/passenger/mile [Diesel Bus Freeway] - 11
gCO2/passenger/mile [EV Bus Freeway])&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id7" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;[2]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id5"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; J. Zhu and Y. Fan, &amp;quot;Commute happiness in Xi'an, China: Effects of
commute mode, duration, and frequency,&amp;quot; Travel Behaviour and Society, vol.
11, pp.  43–51, Apr. 2018.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A. Stutzer and B. S. Frey, &amp;quot;Stress that Doesn't Pay: The Commuting
Paradox*,&amp;quot; The Scandinavian Journal of Economics, vol. 110, no. 2, pp.
339–366, 2008.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id9" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;ol class="first last upperalpha simple" start="19"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handy, &amp;quot;Commute Time as Quality Time,&amp;quot; Transfers, p. 7, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="advocacy"></category><category term="transportation"></category><category term="advocacy"></category><category term="shuttle"></category><category term="commute"></category></entry></feed>